David Sutherland motion picture films relating to Paul Cadmus
Archives of American Art
David Sutherland motion picture films relating to Paul Cadmus
1980-1984
Archives of American Art
Sutherland, David Russell, 1945-
AAA.suthdavi
Archival Resource Key
10.4 Linear feet
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Scope and Contents
Approximately 10 hours of 16mm motion picture and soundtrack outtakes for Sutherland's 1986 film PAUL CADMUS: ENFANT TERRIBLE AT 80, including interviews, footage of Cadmus painting and drawing, and footage from a 1981 retrospective exhibition in Oxford, Ohio. Also found in the collection is a black and white photograph of Cadmus taken by either Sutherland or George Petrakes, June 1980, and a publicity file for the released film.
Biographical / Historical
Filmmaker; Newton, Mass.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated 1984 by David Sutherland.
Painting, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Figurative painting, American -- New York (State) -- New York; Filmmakers -- Massachusetts -- Newton; Cadmus, Paul, 1904-1999
- Trims, Pictures and Sound, Archival Resource Key
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 02)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 03)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 04)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 4, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 05)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 5, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 06)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 6, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 07)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 7, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 08)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 8, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 09)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 9, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 10)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 10, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 11)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 11, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 102)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 12, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 103)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 13, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 104)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 14, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 105)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 15, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 106)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 16, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 107)
    Scope and Contents
    On label: Cadmus on Porch
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 17, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Item FC 108)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 18, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 109)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 19, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 110)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 20, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 111)
    On label: 1st Transfer too fast
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 21, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 112)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 22, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 113)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 23, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 114)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 24, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 115)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 25, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 116)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 26, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 117)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 27, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 118)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 28, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 119)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 29, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 120)
    On label: What I Believe
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 30, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 121)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 31, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 122)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 32, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 123)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 33, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 124)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 34, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 125)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 35, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 126)
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 36, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 127)
    On label: Bar Italia
  - Cadmus Trims, Picture and Sound, reel 37, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 128)
  - Paul Cadmus, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 76)
  - Paul Cadmus, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 77)
- Paul at Gallery, Archival Resource Key
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 12)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts; What I Believe, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 13)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 14)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts; Etchings, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 15)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts; Etchings, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 16)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts, Sound, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 17)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts, Sound; David and Coli Art, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 18)
  - Paul at Gallery, Lifts, Sound; Venus and Adonis, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 19)
  - Paul at Gallery, Outtakes, Sound, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 20)
  - Paul at Gallery, Outtakes, Sound, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 21)
  - Paul at Gallery, Outtakes, Sound; Gilding the Acrobats, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 22)
  - Cadmus at Gallery, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 73)
  - Cadmus at Gallery, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 74)
  - Cadmus at Gallery and Paintings, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 69)
  - Cadmus at Gallery and Paintings, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 70)
- Paul at the beach, Archival Resource Key
  - Paul at the Beach, picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 53)
  - Paul at the Beach, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 54)
  - Paul at the Beach, motion picture outtakes reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 71)
  - Paul at the Beach, motion picture outtakes reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 72)
- Paul on Porch, Archival Resource Key
  - Paul on Porch: Jon in Greenhouse, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 78)
  - Paul on Porch: Jon in Greenhouse, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 79)
- Paul on Painting, Archival Resource Key
  - Paul on Painting: Porch, motion picture reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 82)
  - Paul on Painting: Porch, magnetic track reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 83)
  - Paul on Painting: Porch, motion picture reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 84)
  - Paul on Painting: Porch, magnetic track reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 85)
- Sketching Jon, Archival Resource Key
  - Sketching Jon: Posing, Selects, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 23)
  - Sketching Jon: Posing, Selects, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 24)
  - Sketching Jon: Posing, Selects, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 25)
- The Fleet's In, Archival Resource Key
  - The Fleet's In, Selects, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (Item FC 26)
  - The Fleet's In, Selects, Sound, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 27)
  - The Fleet's In, Lifts; Mo's Motion Picture; Paul at Gallery, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 28)
  - The Fleet's In, Lifts, Sound, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 29)
- Subway, Archival Resource Key
  - Subway, Trims and Outtakes, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel (Item FC 30)
  - Subway, Trims and Outtakes, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 31)
  - Subway, Trims and Outtakes, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 32)
  - Subway, Trims and Outtakes, reel 4, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 33)
  - Subway, Trims and Outtakes, reel 5, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 34)
  - Subway, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 94)
  - Subway, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 95)
- Ohio Opening, Archival Resource Key
  - Ohio Opening Selects, Archival Resource Key
    - Ohio Opening Selects, Motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 35)
    - Ohio Opening Selects, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 36)
  - Ohio Opening, Archival Resource Key
    - Ohio Opening, motion picture, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 37)
    - Ohio Opening, magnetic track, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 38)
    - Ohio Opening, motion picture, reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 39)
    - Ohio Opening, magnetic track, reel 4, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 40)
    - Ohio Opening, magnetic track, reel 5, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 41)
    - Ohio Opening, motion picture, reel 6, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 42)
- Piano, Archival Resource Key
  - Piano, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 45)
  - Piano, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 44)
  - Piano-Commonplace Book, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 50)
  - Piano-Commonplace Book, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 51)
- Commonplace Book, Archival Resource Key
  - Commonplace book quotes, magnetic track, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 47)
  - Commonplace book quotes, magnetic track, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 46)
  - Commonplace book, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 48)
  - Commonplace book, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 49)
- Tempera Painting, Archival Resource Key
  - Tempera Painting, motion picture reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 55)
  - Tempera Painting, magnetic track, reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 56)
  - Tempera Painting, motion picture reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 57)
  - Tempera Painting, magnetic track, reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 58)
  - Egg Yolk Tempera Mixing, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 59)
  - Egg Yolk Tempera Mixing, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 60)
- Driveway, Archival Resource Key
  - Driveway, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 80)
  - Driveway, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 81)
- Sound Elements, Archival Resource Key
  - Mix Elements: Subway Sequence, magnetic sound, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 62)
  - Mix Elements: Subway Sequence, "Cadmus: Dialogue C", 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 63)
  - Mix Elements: Subway Sequence, Scratch Mix, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 64)
  - Cadmus: Rough sketches for music, magnetic track reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 96)
  - Cadmus: Rough sketches for music, magnetic track reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 97)
  - Du Art retransfers magnetic track reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 98)
  - Du Art retransfers magnetic track reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 99)
- E. M. Forster, Archival Resource Key
  - E. M. Forster, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 100)
  - E. M. Forster, magnetic track, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 101)
- Wild Tracks, Archival Resource Key
  - Cadmus: Wild Track uncoded magnetic track reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 65)
  - Cadmus: Wild Track uncoded magnetic track reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 66)
  - Cadmus: Wild Track uncoded magnetic track reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 67)
  - Cadmus: Wild Track uncoded magnetic track reel 4, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 68)
- Drawings and Paintings, Archival Resource Key
  - Drawing and Paintings, motion picture reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 86)
  - Drawing and Paintings, motion picture reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 87)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 1, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 88)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 2, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 89)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 3, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 90)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 4, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 91)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 5, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 92)
  - Paintings, motion picture reel 6, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 93)
- Scrapbook Clippings, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 43)
- Photos and Paintings, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 52)
- Night in Bologna, motion picture, 1984; Archival Resource Key; 1 Film reel 16mm (Item FC 75)